<tool id="super_distance" name="Super_distance" version="@VERSION@">
  <description>Supertree estimation using matrix representation with distances </description>
    <macros>
        <import>macros.xml</import>
    </macros>
    <expand macro="requirements" />
    <expand macro="version_command" />
    <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
      #set $spaced_input = ''
      #for $i_file in $inputtre:
        #set $_input_file = "'{}'".format($i_file)
        #set $spaced_input = $spaced_input + ' ' + $_input_file
      #end for

      super_distance $fast
      #if str($spnames) != ""
      -s $spnames
      #end if
      -o ./all.tre 
      ${spaced_input} &&
      #if str($fast) != ""
        sed -n '1p' ./all.tre > ./nodal.tre &&
        sed -n '2p' ./all.tre > ./average.tre
      #else
        sed -n '3p' ./all.tre > ./nodal.tre &&
        sed -n '9p' ./all.tre > ./average.tre
      #end if

    ]]></command>
  <inputs>
    <param name="inputtre" multiple="true" type="data" format="nhx" label="input (gene) trees in newick format (can have more than one tree per file)"/>

    <param name="spnames" type="data" format="txt,tabular" label="File with list of species names" optional="true">
      <help><![CDATA[
        This file is optional, but highly recommended unless all trees came from same dataset (leaves have same names etc.). 
        This list will define leaves in species tree, and allow for paralogs (i.e. several leaves in gene tree with same label).
        ]]></help>
    </param>

    <param name="fast" type="boolean" truevalue="--fast" falsevalue="" checked="true" label="Fast estimation (for large supertrees)">
      <help><![CDATA[
        If you don't chose fast estimation, a lot of trees will be output to same file, which must then  be inspected by user. 
        The first two trees from this file are collected as individual tree files. The fast option is in theory 18x faster than the regular run, since 
        it estimates only 2 instead of 36 species trees (assuming UPGMA/NJ is the overwhelming step). 
        ]]></help>
    </param>

    <param name="epslon" type="float" label="polytomy tolerance" min="0.0" optional="true">
      <help><![CDATA[ 
        Small value, below which a branch length is considered zero for nodal distances. Default is 1e-7. 
        ]]></help>
    </param>
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
     <data name="alltrees" format="nhx" label="All supertrees" from_work_dir="all.tre" />
     <data name="nodaltree" format="nhx" label="Nodal supertree" from_work_dir="nodal.tre" />
     <data name="averagetree" format="nhx" label="Average supertree" from_work_dir="average.tre" />

  </outputs>
  <tests>
    <test>
      <param name="spnames" value="species_names.txt"/>
      <param name="fast" value="true"/>
      <param name="inputtre" value="HOG1.tre,HOG2.tre,HOG3.tre,HOG4.tre,HOG5.tre"/>
      <output name='nodaltree'>
        <assert_contents><has_text_matching expression="[F00]"/></assert_contents>
      </output>
      <output name='averagetree'>
        <assert_contents><has_text_matching expression="[F01]"/></assert_contents>
      </output>
    </test>
  </tests>
    <help><![CDATA[
      Matrix Representation with Distances: calculates pairwise distances between gene leaves, and estimates species trees from summary distance matrices 
      This software implements a class of methods called Matrix Representation with Distances (MRD), with emphasis on whole 
      gene families (i.e. gene trees that may contain paralogs) for species tree inference. 
      The two main output trees are the *Nodal* and the *Average* supertrees. If the "--fast" option was not selected, then the file *All* 
      supertrees will have several other estimates (otherwise it will have only the two main supertrees).

      
      The "Nodal" supertree is estimated from nodal distances betweeen gene tree leaves (equivalent to assuming equal branch lengths), but its final branch lengths 
      are estimated by least squares using the average branch lengths. The "Average" supertree uses this information directly, and both supertrees are estimated by 
      UPGMA.
      

      super_distance  [-h|--help] [-v|--version] [-F|--fast] [-e|--epsilon=<double>] [-s|--species=<species names>] [-o|--output=<newick>] <file> [<file>]...

      Based on several rescaled patristic distances, the program takes the average matrix between genes and estimates
      the species tree using bioNJ, UPGMA and single-linkage after scaling back to the original values (more below). The program 
      also uses a distance matrix to project branch lengths on species trees missing lengths; 

      The branch length rescaling per gene can be the minimum, the average, the total sum, etc. and at the end these values
      averaged over trees are scaled back in the final distance matrix, such that lengths in the supertree (species tree) are interpretable.
      One exception is the nodal distance, which is based on the number of nodes between two leaves (e.g. NJst). In this case it may make
      more sense to use another distance matrix to infer the branch lengths. Option 'F' uses averages distances projected on nodal-estimated tree; 
      it uses fewer scalings/options, providing a fast estimation. We avoid using individual gene trees since they may have 
      missing information (missing species or species pairs). For missing comparisons (when two species are never seen in the same gene tree)
      we use the ultrametric condition (comparison to a common species) to estimate its value.

      If a file with species names is given, the program allows for paralogs; otherwise it assumes orthology and that _at_least_ one tree has no missing data:
      * Paralogy: the species names will be mapped to individual gene tree leaves (e.g. `ECOLI_a` and `ECOLI_b` will both map to species `ECOLI`).
      Each gene tree can therefore have several copies of each species, and can also have missing species.
      * Orthology: if a file with species names is not given, however, it is assumed that each species is represented at most once per gene, and
      furthermore that the leaf names represent the species, and are thus identical across trees. This mode is the underlying assumption behind
      most tree comparison software, although here missing data for some trees (not all) is allowed. I.e. as long as one tree has full information
      (for all species), then others can have some absent species.
      With paralogs or not, it is not recommended to have missing entries in the distance matrix (e.g. when a species pair does not appear in any tree),
      and matrix representation with distances methods work better with more 'complete' gene trees. If there are no paralogs, many supertrees will be equivalent, 
      as well as if the input trees lack lengths (only topological information).

    ]]></help>
    <expand macro="citations" />
</tool>
